A Guide to the Virginia. Dept. of General Services. Division of Engineering and Buildings, Woodrow Wilson General Hospital (now Woodrow Wilson Rehabilitation Center), Architectural drawings, 1937-1959
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia. Dept. of General Services. Division of Engineering and Buildings, Woodrow Wilson General Hospital, Architectural drawings, 1937-1959
The Library of Virginia
32377
2.5 cu. ft. [2 boxes; 149 sheets]
Virginia. Dept. of General Services. Division of Engineering and Buildings.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred 25 April 1985 from the Dept. of General Services, Div. of Engineering and Buildings, 805 E. Broad St., Room 101, Richmond, Va. 23219
Biographical Information
The mission of the Dept. of General Services is to provide supportive services to other state agencies, local political subdivisions as appropriate, in the areas of laboratory services; maintenance, operation and construction of facilities; land management; land and facilities acquisition; disposal and sale of material and supplies; risk management; and other related activities. The Commission on State Governmental Management recommended the creation of the Dept. of General Services to be comprised of the then existing Dept. of Purchases and Supplies, Division of Engineering and Buildings, Division of Consolidated Laboratory Services, Dept. of Property Records and Insurance, and several other state agencies functions which were subsequently determined by appropriate authorities to be left outside of the organization of this department.
In 1976, the General Assembly passed H.B. 1240 which called for the establishment of the position of a director of the department and required the appointee to prepare a plan for the organization of this department with implementing legislation. This was accomplished and the 1977 session of the General Assembly enacted Chapter 672 which created the Dept. of General Services. Consistent with this statute, the department was officially implemented on July 1, 1978. This brought together, under the umbrella of the major department, the Dept. of Purchases and Supply, the Division of Engineering, the Division of Consolidated Laboratory Services, and the Dept. of Property Records and Insurance, now called Office of Risk Management. Also included under the umbrella of the authority of the Dept. of General Services are several boards, appeal boards and review councils which are: Consolidated Laboratory Services Advisory Board; Purchase and Supply Appeal Board; Art and Architectural Review and Council and the State Insurance Advisory Board.
Major activities of the department are to maintain and operate facilities at the seat of government; assist in the administration of the capital outlay budget of the Commonwealth; to assist in acquisition of real property either by lease or purchase; to perform centralized purchasing functions of the Commonwealth; to dispose of surplus real property and material and supplies; to provide a comprehensive risk management insurance program for all agencies and institutions; to operate a centralized purchasing and warehousing function for supplying State agencies and certain political subdivisions with equipment and supplies; to acquire or provide printing services for State agencies and institutions; provide central mail and messenger service for State agencies in the area of the seat of government; provide laboratory research and scientific services in the area of environmental sciences; forensic science, microbiology, and product regulation; to provide training to law enforcement personnel in the collection and preservation of evidence; and to conduct programs on inspection and certification of certain laboratories through the state.
Scope and Content
This collection contains 149 sheets of architectural drawings and plans for the Woodrow Wilson General Hospital (now Woodrow Wilson Rehabilitation Center) in Fishersville, Virginia. Most of the plans were executed by the United States War Department, United States Engineer's Office, the United States Office of the Quartermaster, the firm of Perring & Remington, or the Commonwealth of Virginia- Division of the Budget- Section of Institutional Engineering. These plans depict many of the structures on the grounds of the hospital before and after they were taken over by the Commonwealth of Virginia.
In 1946, the General Assembly of Virginia adopted Senate Joint Resolution No. 4, creating a commission to study the use of the property as a Tuberculosis Sanatorium or other purposes. Originally a United States Army Hospital for war-injured soldiers, the property was declared surplus by the federal government and sold to the Commonwealth in 1947. Virginia operated the facility as a hospital for tuberculosis patients and a rehabilitation center for disabled individuals.
The hospital's campus underwent an extensive renovation in the 1960s and 1970s and many of the original structures were replaced with modern buildings. The drawings in this group represent many of the pre- and post-WWII buildings that are no longer extant.
Contents List
- Bldg. # 401.1, Hospital Barracks (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 412.2, Administration Bldg. (1), 1941 May 24, rev. 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 414.1, Recreation Bldg. (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 416.1, Morgue (1), 1943 February 16 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 503.2, Service Club for Officers (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 508.2, Hospital Mess (2), 1942 May 26 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 611.4, Heating, Blackout & Plumbing (3), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 613.2, Ward (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 614.1, Heating Plant (4), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 614.2, Heating Plant Architectural & Heating (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 802.1, Store House (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 809.1, Refrigerated Unit (1), 1942 July 22, rev. 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 813.1, Hospital Shop (2), 1942 February 28 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 814.1, Utility Shop (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 816.1, Fire Station & Laundry (4), 1942 September 2 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 817.2, Guard House (1), 1937 May 5 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 818.1, Utility Shop (3), 1943 March 29 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 205.8, Foundation for Control Panel (1), 1958 December 10 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 205.9, Suggested Control Wiring (1), 1959 July 9 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 205.10, Improvements, Coal Handling Eqpmt. (1), 1959 September 16 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 205.7, New Keeler Boiler Installation (2), 1958 December 5 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 205.5, Space for New 12,500 #/HR Boiler (1), 1958 April 28 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 205.4, Isometric Showing Boiler Foundation (1), n.d. (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 101.1, Plumbing Changes - Admin. Bldg. (1), 1942 October 22 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 101.2, Blackout Lights, 1943 January 16 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 101.3, Architectural - Admin. Bldg. (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 102.1, Hospital Quarters (4), rev. 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 103.2, Officer's Quarters-Foundation (1), 1942 September 5 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 103.4, Plumbing Changes (1), 1942 October 30, rev. 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 201.2, Blackout Lights (1), 1937 January 16 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 321.2, Blackout Lights (1), 1943 January 6 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 202.2, Ward Building (1), 1942 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 201.1, Ward-Standard (1), 1937 May 5 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 208.1, Ward (1), 1942 September 5 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 209.1, Ward (1), 1942 September 5 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 211.1, Chapel (4), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 214.1, Ward (1), 1942 September 5 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 215.1, Patients' Effects Bldg. (2), 1943 February 11 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 216.1, Pump Pits 1 & 2 (1), 1942 August 1 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 215.2, Canteen Equipment (5), 1957 February (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 217.1, Receiving Building (2), 1943 February 11 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 301.2, Clinic & Surgery (4), 1941 September 18, rev. 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 307.1, Physiotherapy Bldg. (1), 1937 May 5, rev. 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 311.4, Sprinkler System-Activities Bldg. (1), 1956 June 21 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 314.1, Telephone & Ambulance Garage (1), 1942 August 1 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 321.5, Dishwashing Equipment (2), 1953 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 321.6, Addition to Dining Hall (10), 1954 November 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 713.1, Post Office (1), 1942 August 1 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 824.1, Storehouse (1), 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 826.1, Paint Shops (1), 1942 February 28, rev. 1943 May 15 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 902.1, Gymnasium Bldg. (2), 1943 November 10 (Box 1)
- Bldg. # 99.1, Sewage Treatment Plant-Plan (6), 1942 August 15 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 904.2, Swimming Pool (5), 1945 May 5 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 611.2, Detention Ward-Heating (1), 1941 August 12 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 822.1, Hospital Laundry-Plumbing (1), 1941 March 26, rev. 1942 July 14 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 822.2, Hospital Utilities (4), 1941 December 11, rev. 1943 October 21 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 205.1, Boiler House (1), 1940 August 16, rev. 1941 July 30 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 205.2, 1-253 HP V.I.W. Long (1), 1942 October 20 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 205.3, Heating Plant-Architectural (4), 1943 May 15 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 102.2, Plumbing Revisions (2), 1943 May 15 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 202.3, Ward (4), 1942 November 30, rev. 1943 October 14 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 311.2, Activities Bldg. (11), 1956 March 20 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 314.3, Heating & Electrical Plan (1), 1942 September 30 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 321.3, Mess Hall (4), 1943 May 15 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 321.4, Storeroom-Mess Hall (1), 1954 July 20 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 201.1, Ward-Standard (1), 1937 May 5, rev. 1941 March 29 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # 903.1, Swimming Pool (11), 1945 May 4 (Box 2)
- Bldg. # Misc. 15, Mobilization Bldg.- Stnd. Details (5), 1943 May 15, rev. 1945 April 2 (Box 2)